Guide to the Phil Lelli Papers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Phil Lelli papers
1933-2004
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections
5536
5536-001
Lelli, Phil,$d1929-2004
10.45 cubic feet 11 boxes and 1 vertical file
Papers of a longshoreman, union leader, and president of the Local # 23, International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union (ILWU)
Philip Martin Lelli (1929-2004) was a longshoreman, union activist, local philanthropist, and past president of the ILWU Local 23, in Tacoma, Washington.
Born in Tacoma on December 4, 1929, Lelli was raised in the Edgewood Area. His parents, Martin (nicknamed "Barney") and Mary Ballard, ran Lelli's Grocery. He attended Edgemont School (now Edgewood), Fife High School (graduating in 1947), and Pacific Lutheran University. In 1953 he married B. Joann Williams and had 5 sons.
Lelli joined the Tacoma area longshoremen union in September 1956 after spending a few years in the construction industry in various parts of Washington and Alaska. In 1961 he took his first gear locker job at Rothschild Stevedoring, later known at Jones Washington Stevedoring Company, with T. A. "Tiny" Thronson in the Tacoma shop. Lelli was elected president of the ILWU Local 23, a position which he held for 17 inconsecutive years, from 1966-1969, 1971-1975, and 1977-1986. According to one biographical document, he attended his first ILWU Longshore, Shipclerk, and Walking Boss Caucus in 1966. Lelli served on various ILWU committees, including the Coast Negotiating Committee (elected in 1989), and was appointed to the Pacific Coast Safety Committee as a representative of the Washington area. He also served as an ILWU delegate to New Zealand and Australia in 1983.
Lelli's other activities included serving on the Washington State Advisory Council on International Trade and Development from 1983-1985 and serving as an appointed Port of Tacoma commissioner beginning in 1992. He also was a member of the Tacoma Propeller Club and served as president in 1977, the first member from labor to ever hold that office in the national club history.
Arranged in 5 series:
International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union (ILWU)
Port of Tacoma
Propeller Club of America
Subject files
Personal papers
Papers concerning Lelli's career as a longshoreman, union leader, and president of the Local # 23, International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union (ILWU).
Open to all users.
Source: Joann Lelli via Dean Lelli, 2008.
Lelli, Phil,$d1929-2004$vArchives; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Fraternal organizations$zPacific Coast (U.S.); Industrial relations$zWashington (State); Stevedores$xLabor unions$zWashington (State)$zTacoma
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor Unions; Labor History; Ships and Shipping; Washington (State); Tacoma
- International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union (ILWU)
  - Convention
    - Photograph - Pacific Coast District, 1941 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Brochures, 1965 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Report - Publicity and Education Committee, 1965 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Resolutions and Statements of Policy, 1965 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Roster of Delegates, 1965 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Summarized Minutes, 1965 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Address - Louis Goldblatt, 1967 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Address - Mark O. Hatfield, 1967 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Letters and Messages, 1967 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Press Releases, 1967 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Recommendations and Amendments, 1967 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Reports, 1967 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Resolutions and Drafts of Resolutions, 1967 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Roster of Delegates, 1967 (Box-folder 1/14)
    - Rules, 1967 (Box-folder 1/15)
    - Statement of Policy - Drafts, 1967 (Box-folder 1/16)
    - Statement of Policy, 1967 (Box-folder 1/17)
    - Summarized Minutes, 1967 (Box-folder 1/18)
    - Address - Anatoly Baranovsky and George Oleshkevich, 1975 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Address - Joe Morris, 1975 (Box-folder 1/20)
    - Constitution Committee, 1975 (Box-folder 1/21)
    - Reports, 1975 (Box-folder 1/22)
    - Resolutions, 1975 (Box-folder 1/23)
    - Roster of Delegates, 1975 (Box-folder 1/24)
    - Statement of Policy, 1975 (Box-folder 1/25)
    - Summarized Minutes, 1975 (Box-folder 1/26)
    - Summarized Minutes, 1977 (Box-folder 1/27)
    - Address - Senator Julian Bond, 1981 (Box-folder 1/28)
    - Call, 1983 (Box-folder 1/29)
    - Documents, 1983 (Box-folder 1/30)
    - Call, 1985 (Box-folder 1/31)
    - Committee Assignments, 1985 (Box-folder 1/32)
    - Documents, 1985 (Box-folder 1/33)
    - Reports, 1985 (Box-folder 1/34)
    - Resolutions and Statements of Policy, 1985 (Box-folder 1/35)
    - Roster of Delegates, 1985 (Box-folder 1/36)
    - Roster of Fraternals, 1985 (Box-folder 1/37)
    - Rules, 1985 (Box-folder 1/38)
    - Summarized Minutes, 1985 (Box-folder 1/39)
    - Address - Jack Henning, 1988 (Box-folder 1/40)
    - Press Release, 1988 (Box-folder 1/41)
    - Principles of Autonomy & Jurisdictional Integrity within the AFL-CIO, 1988 (Box-folder 1/42)
    - Roster of Delegates, 1988 (Box-folder 1/43)
    - Statements of Policy and Resolution, 1988 (Box-folder 1/44)
    - Agenda, 1991 (Box-folder 1/45)
    - Documents, 1991 (Box-folder 1/46)
    - Reports, 1991 (Box-folder 1/47)
    - Resolutions and Statement of Policy, 1991 (Box-folder 1/48)
    - Roster - Constitution Committee, 1991 (Box-folder 1/49)
    - Roster of Delegates, 1991 (Box-folder 1/50)
    - Rules, [1991?] (Box-folder 1/51)
    - Summarized Minutes, 1991 (Box-folder 1/52)
  - Longshore, Clerk, and Walking Bosses Caucus
    - Misc. Files, 1965 April - 1966 July (Box-folder 1/53-70)
    - Misc. Files, 1966 July - 1973 May (Box 2)
    - Misc. Files, 1973 June- 1984 July (Box 3)
    - Misc. Files, 1984 July - 1993 March (Box 4)
    - Misc. Files, 1993 July - 2002 December (Box-folder 5/1-7)
    - Notes, undated (Box-folder 5/8-14)
  - Pacific Maritime Association, 1965 - 2002 (Box-folder 5/15-36)
  - Teamsters, 1966; 1984 (Box-folder 5/37-38)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 5/39-46)
  - Committees
    - Coast Area Education Committee, 2002-2004 (Box-folder 5/47-48)
    - Coast Legislative Action Committee, 2002 (Box-folder 5/49-50)
    - Coast Pro Rata Committee, 1977-1981 (Box-folder 5/51-53)
    - Labor Relations Committee, Area and Local, 1960-2002 (Box-folder 6/1-13)
    - Longshore Barge Committee, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 6/14)
    - Longshore Safety Negotiating Committee, 1985-1999 (Box-folder 6/15-18)
    - Longshore Safety Negotiating Committee, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 7/1-2)
    - Pacific Coast Pensioners Association, 1995-2002 (Box-folder 7/3-10)
  - Local #23
    - Agreement - Checkers and Supervisors, 1956, undated (Box-folder 7/11)
    - Agreement - Working and Dispatching Rules (supplemental), 1959 (Box-folder 7/12)
    - Agreement - Working and Dispatching Rules, 1967 (Box-folder 7/13)
    - Award for Lelli (photocopy), 1985 (Box-folder 7/14)
    - Constitution, undated (Box-folder 7/15)
    - Correspondence, 1933, 1981-1992, undated (Box-folder 7/16)
    - Correspondence - Bellingham Stevedoring Co., 1966 (Box-folder 7/17)
    - Correspondence - Lelli - Outgoing, 1978-2002 (Box-folder 7/18)
    - Correspondence - Lelli - Outgoing, undated (Box-folder 7/19)
    - Correspondence - Lelli - Incoming, undated (Box-folder 7/20)
    - Correspondence Drafts - Lelli, undated (Box-folder 7/21)
    - Correspondence - Tacoma Joint Labor Relations Committee, 1964 (Box-folder 7/22)
    - Documents - Centennial, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 7/23)
    - Documents - Centennial, 1986 (Box-folder 7/24)
    - Documents - Dispute with Local #52, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 7/25)
    - Documents - DuPont, undated (Box-folder 7/26)
    - Documents - Political Action Committee, circa 1986 (Box-folder 7/27)
    - Documents - President Ronald Reagan's Visit, undated (Box-folder 7/28)
    - Documents - Misc., undated (Box-folder 7/29-30)
    - Financial Report, 1974 (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Histories, 1989, 1991, undated (Box-folder 8/2)
    - Letter - "The Concerned Committee", undated (Box-folder 8/3)
    - Member Death Lists, undated (Box-folder 8/4)
    - Member List - "A" men and "B" men, undated (Box-folder 8/5)
    - Membership Roll, 1886-1989, undated (Box-folder 8/6)
    - Memorial - Dave Johnson, undated (Box-folder 8/7)
    - Minutes, 1975 December (Box-folder 8/8)
    - Nicknames, undated (Box-folder 8/9)
    - Notebooks - Lelli, undated (Box-folder 8/10-11)
    - Resolutions, 1966, 1967 (Box-folder 8/12-13)
    - Resolutions Submitted, 1970, circa 1978, circa 1984 (Box-folder 8/14-16)
    - Rules, 1959, circa 1965 (Box-folder 8/17)
    - Statements - Phil Lelli, undated (Box-folder 8/18)
    - Writings - Phil Lelli, undated (Box-folder 8/19-20)
  - Travel related to ILWU
    - Photographs, undated (Box-folder 8/21)
    - Documents - Misc., 1982, 1989, undated (Box-folder 8/22)
    - Waterfront Industry Tribunal Decisions (New Zealand), 1982 (Box-folder 8/23)
    - Brochures, Misc.(New Zealand), 1982 (Box-folder 8/24)
    - Photograph - New Zealand Waterside Workers' Federation, 1982
    - Letter of Introduction, Newspaper Clippings (Russia), 1988 (Box-folder 8/25)
    - Journal, Photographs, Misc. (Russia), 1988 (Box-folder 8/26)
    - Exhibition Guide, Misc. (Italy), 1992 (Box-folder 8/27)
    - Publications - China Portex '92, 1993 (Box-folder 8/28)
    - Publications - Opaeha Nehnha, 1985 (Box-folder 8/29)
- Port of Tacoma
  - Articles of Agreement, undated (Box-folder 9/1)
  - Brochure - Port of Tacoma, circa 1967 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Brochure - Working Waterfront Museum, undated (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Clippings, 1982-1986, undated (Box-folder 9/4)
  - Constitution, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 9/5)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1972, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 9/6)
  - Data File '92, 1992 (Box-folder 9/7)
  - Documents - Log Export, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 9/8)
  - Documents - Puyallup Indian Tribe Settlement, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 9/9)
  - Documents - Misc., circa 1967-1990s (Box-folder 9/10-11)
  - Drawings, 1986-1987, undated (Box-folder 9/12)
  - Economic Impact Study, 1988 (Box-folder 9/13)
  - Employee Benefits Guide, 1991 (Box-folder 9/14-15)
  - Financial Summary, 1992 (Box-folder 9/16)
  - Financial Report, 1992 (Box-folder 9/17)
  - Knowing the Waters: Basic Legal Guidelines for Port District Officials, 1985 (Box-folder 9/18)
  - Memoradum, 1974, 1980-1981, 1993 (Box-folder 9/19)
  - Memorandum from Scott Ford, 1975 (Box-folder 9/20)
  - News Bulletin, 1974 (Box-folder 9/21)
  - On the Waterfront, 1987, 1987 (Box-folder 9/22)
  - Organizational Flow Chart, 1975 (Box-folder 9/23)
  - Photographs - Bird's-eye-views, undated (Box-folder 9/24)
  - Photographs, undated (Box-folder 9/25)
  - Photographs - Proposed Sea-Land Terminal, undated (Box-folder 9/26)
  - Photographs - Proposed TOTE Terminal Site, undated (Box-folder 9/27)
  - Photographs - Old Equipment, undated (Box-folder 9/28)
  - Photographs - Snapshots, undated (Box-folder 9/29)
  - Port Commissioner, circa 1980 (Box-folder 9/30)
  - Port Commissioner - Supporter address lists, 1990-1993 (Box-folder 9/31)
  - Port Commissioner - Application, 1993 (Box-folder 9/32-33)
  - Port Commissioner - Briefing, 1992 (Box-folder 9/34)
  - Port Commissioner - Robert Earley, circa 1995 (Box-folder 9/35)
  - Report - 1991 Washington Ports and Transportation Systems Study (Box-folder 9/36)
  - Report - Port Consolidation, 1982 (Box-folder 9/37)
  - Study - Sales and Marketing Program, undated (Box-folder 9/38)
- Propeller Club of America
  - Port of Tacoma Chapter
    - Building Dedication, 1988 (Box-folder 10/1)
    - Building Development Plans, undated (Box-folder 10/2)
    - Bylaws, undated (Box-folder 10/3)
    - Chowdown, 1995-2003, undated (Box-folder 10/4-7)
    - Chowdown - Financial Report, 1991 (Box-folder 10/8)
    - Chowdown - Clippings, 1992 (Box-folder 10/9)
    - Chowdown - Programs, undated (Box-folder 10/10)
    - Directories, undated (Box-folder 10/11)
    - Documents - Administrative, undated (Box-folder 10/12)
    - Documents - Misc., undated (Box-folder 10/13)
    - Guidelines for Port Officers, undated (Box-folder 10/14)
    - Membership Application, undated (Box-folder 10/15)
    - Memoradum, undated (Box-folder 10/16)
    - Minutes, undated (Box-folder 10/17)
    - Newsletters, undated (Box-folder 10/18)
    - Photographs, circa 1975-1997, undated (Box-folder 10/19-20)
    - Ross E. Lelli Scholarship, undated (Box-folder 10/21)
  - National
    - Application - Maritime Week Luncheon (Box-folder 10/22)
    - Convention Program, 1976 (Box-folder 10/23)
    - Convention Registration List, 1991 (Box-folder 10/24)
- Subject Files
  - Pacific Maritime Association
    - Annual Report, 2002 (Box-folder 10/25)
    - Booklet (photocopy) - Rothschild International Stevedoring Company Centennial, circa 1958 (Box-folder 10/26)
    - Bulletins - PMA Update Vol 9, nos. 1-5, 7-8, 1997 (Box-folder 10/27)
    - Clippings, 1954-2002 (Box-folder 10/28)
    - Datasets, Memos, and Misc. Documents, undated (Box-folder 10/29)
    - Maust Corporation, 1987 (Box-folder 10/30)
    - Periodical (photocopy) Marine Digest Vol. 62, No. 18 (Box-folder 10/31)
    - Photograph, undated (Box-folder 10/32)
    - Rothschild Washington Stevedoring Company, undated (Box-folder 10/33)
  - Washington State Advisory Council
    - Documents, circa 1984 (Box-folder 10/34-35)
- Personal papers
  - Biographical, undated (Box-folder 10/36)
  - Clippings - about Lelli, undated (Box-folder 10/37)
  - Correspondence - about Lelli career and achievements, 1980-2002 (Box-folder 10/38)
  - Documents - Relating to Ralph Chaplin, 1961-1990 (Box-folder 10/39)
  - Documents - Harry Bridges Chair at the University of Washington, 1990-2003 (Box-folder 10/40-41)
  - Documents - Ernie Tanner Center, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 11/1)
  - Documents - Misc., undated (Box-folder 11/2)
  - Drawing - Lelli's Grocery, undated (Box-folder 11/3)
  - Event Invitations and Programs, undated (Box-folder 11/4)
  - Photographs - Event and Places, undated (Box-folder 11/5)
  - Photographs - Portraits, undated (Box-folder 11/6)
  - Photographs - U.S. Army Hospital Ship, "Marigold", undated (Box-folder 11/7)
  - Photographs - "W.T. Preston", 1981 (Box-folder 11/8)
  - Photograph and Documents - "USS Jeremiah O'Brien", 1996 (Box-folder 11/9)
  - Retirement Party, 1992 (Box-folder 11/10-11)
  - Retirement Party - Guest Book, 1992 (Box-folder 11/12)
  - Writings - B. Joann Lelli, undated (Box-folder 11/13)
  - Writings - Phil Lelli, undated (Box-folder 11/14)